Guide to the Southwell Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Southwell papers
1660-1750
1660-1700
OSB MSS 41
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence and other documents mostly pertaining to Southwell's diplomatic career and his landholdings in Ireland. Subjects of the correspondence include his negotiations during his missions to Lisbon and Brandenburg; trade with the East Indies; the Revolution of 1688; unrest in Ireland; and the management of Southwell's Irish estates. Major correspondents include Don Marco Barry, Sir Richard Bulstrode, Francis Holbeck, and Bernardo de Salinas. The collection also contains memoranda and notes by Southwell on diplomatic and religious subjects. Other papers include a 1670 auction list from Charing Cross; Archbishop Sancroft's declaration concerning the nonjuring bishops; an account of the state of South Sea Stock in 1720; and a memorandum on trade with Sweden.
Southwell, Robert, Sir, 1635-1702
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Robert Southwell was born near Kinsale, Ireland, and educated at Queen's College, Oxford. Knighted in 1665 and appointed envoy to the court of Portugal, Southwell successfully concluded the Peace of Lisbon in 1668. He held several other diplomatic posts under James II, including envoy to Lisbon again, and then to Brussels and Brandenburg. In 1690 he accompanied William III to Ireland and was named principal secretary of state for that kingdom, an office he held until his death. In 1690 he was elected President of the Royal Society. He died at King's Weston in Glocestershire.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence and other documents mostly pertaining to Southwell's diplomatic career and his landholdings in Ireland. Subjects of the correspondence include his negotiations during his missions to Lisbon and Brandenburg; trade with the East Indies; the Revolution of 1688; unrest in Ireland; and the management of Southwell's Irish estates. Major correspondents include Don Marco Barry, Sir Richard Bulstrode, Francis Holbeck, and Bernardo de Salinas. The collection also contains memoranda and notes by Southwell on diplomatic and religious subjects.
Other papers include a 1670 auction list from Charing Cross; Archbishop Sancroft's declaration concerning the nonjuring bishops; an account of the state of South Sea Stock in 1720; and a memorandum on trade with Sweden.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by author or title.
Diplomatic and consular service, British; Land tenure -- Ireland; Landlord and tenant -- Ireland; Europe -- History -- 1648-1715; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- 1660-1714; Great Britain -- History -- 1689-1714; Great Britain -- History -- Restoration, 1660-1688; Ireland -- History -- War of 1689-1691; Ireland -- Social conditions; Portugal -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Diplomats -- Great Britain; William, King of England, III, 1650-1702; Avaux, comte d', 1640-1709; Barnes, Thomas; Barry, Marco; Blathwayt, William, 1649?-1717; Bulstrode, Richard, Sir, 1610-1711; Ellis, John, 1642 or 1643-1738; Holbeck, Francis; Sancroft, William, 1617-1693; South Sea Company
- Box and Folder List
  - Abingdon, Montagu Venables-Bertie, 2d Earl of, d. 1743. ALS to Edward Southwell, London, 1704 Jan 11 (Box 1)
  - "Alterations to be made in the Comissions of the Peace", [1688] (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Anonymous manuscript.
  - Anon. AL to the Countess of Clancarty, [n.p.], 1697 Aug 27 (Box 1)
  - Anon. AL to Lord Ormonde, [n.p.] (Box 1)
  - Anon. 2 AL to Sir Robert Southwell, Antwerp, 1673 Feb 6, Mar 7 (Box 1)
  - Archer, William. ALS to Colebroke & Co., [n.p.], 1719 Mar 13 (Box 1)
  - Ardglass, Thomas Cromwell, 3d Earl of, 1653-1682. [Abstract of patent granting scite], [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, T. 4 ALS to Edward Southwell, Whitehall, 1703 Dec 28-1704 Feb 8 (Box 1)
  - "Att the Royall house by Charing Cross on Thursday the 29th of May are to [be] sold these ...", [ca. 1670] (Box 1)
  - Avaux, Jean Antoine de Maesmes, Comte d', 1640-1709. Memorial to the Estates General, The Hague, 1684 Jun 5 (Box 1)
  - Aylmer, Sir Justin. [Case for Lord Ormonde], [n.p.] (Box 1)
  - Balzac, Jean Louis Guez de, 1594-1654. Letter (copy) to [Marie de Jars de?], Gournay, 1644 Apr 29 (Box 1)
  - Barnes, Thomas. 7 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Gravesend, Lisbon, 1670 Mar 15-May 29 (Box 1)
  - Barry, Don Marco. 11 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Lisbon, 1669 Jun 15-1671 Apr 28 (Box 1)
  - Basburgh, Joseph. ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, [n.p.], 1672 Nov 29 (Box 1)
  - Beaufort, Henry Somerset, 1st Duke of, 1629-1700
    - ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Chelsea, 1682 Dec 11 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Badminton, 1685 Aug 21 (Box 1)
  - Blathwayt, William, 1649?-1717. ALS to [?], Durham, [ca. 1680] (Box 1)
  - "A Briefe of the Case Betweene Thomas Lewis and Luke Norton", [ca. 1680] (Box 1)
  - Bulstrode, Sir Richard, 1610-1711. 7 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Antwerp, 1673 Jul 16/23, 1674 Feb 20 (Box 1)
  - Carteret, Sir Philip de. [Homage to King Charles], Westminster, 1676 May 25 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield, Philip Stanhope, 2d Earl of, 1633-1713. Letter to Sir Robert Southwell, Brebby, 1686/7 Mar 8 (Box 1)
  - Cox, Richard. ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Dublin, [1671 or later] (Box 1)
  - Crafford, Barnabe. ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Lyra, 1673 May 1 (Box 1)
  - Dungannon, Mark Trevor, 3d Viscount, 1669-1706. ALS to Edward Southwell, [n.p.], 1705 Jun 23 (Box 1)
  - Ellis, John, 1643?-1738
    - 3 ALS to Edward Southwell, Whitehall, 1704 Jan 25-Dec 9 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, London, 1689 Sep 19 (Box 1)
  - "Extract from the Survey Book and Court Rolls of the Mannor [of Dorking] as to Several Copyhold Estates of the late Earl of Rockingham", [1746] (Box 1)
    Contemporary manuscript copy.
  - Faral, Richard. ALS to [?], Florence, 1661 May 3 (Box 1)
  - Fitzgerald, Richard. ALS to Robert Southwell, Madrid, 1669 Oct 16 (Box 1)
  - Godfrey, Thomas. [Receipt for £18 for Lady Ellinor Arthur], Thoydon Garnon, 1672 Jul 11 (Box 1)
  - Godolphin, Sidney Godolphin, 1st Earl of, 1645-1712
    - ALS to Lord Ormonde, [n.p.], 1703 Jul 9 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Whitehall, 1684 Jul 22 (Box 1)
    - [Announcement of the Office of Comptroller of Accounts], Windsor Castle, 1703 Jun 26 (Box 1)
  - Granville, John Granville, Baron, 1665-1707. ALS to Lord [Ormonde?], St. James's, 1703 Jun 15 (Box 1)
  - Gt. Brit. Exchequer. [Memorandum on the case of Thomas Dongan vs. Lucas Santen], 1687 Jul 29 (Box 1)
  - Gt. Brit. Treasury. "Copy of the Presentment made to the Lords of the Treasury about the Ships outward bound laden with Lead ...", 1689 Dec (Box 1)
  - Hamilton, Hans. [Reply to Sir William Johnston's petition to Commons against his election in Nervy], [n.p.], n.d. (Box 2)
  - Holbeck, Francis. 5 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Lisbon, 1669 Jul 25-1670 Mar 24 (Box 2)
  - Hughes, Owen. 3 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Norwich, 1672 Dec 23-1673 Sep 26 (Box 2)
  - [Indenture between Richard Foordge and John Driver in Woolston], [1603?-25?] (Box 2)
  - Ireland. Court of Chancery. "An Account of Fiants sealed from the 24th day of June 1741 ... to the 24th of June 1742", 1741-42 (Box 2)
  - Jones, Jezreel, d. 1731. ALS to Edward Southwell, Rough Court, 1720 Jun 1 (Box 2)
  - Jones, Roger. 6 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Antwerp, 1672 Sep 24-1674 Feb 6 (Box 2)
  - LeGrand, Edward. 2 ALS to Edward Southwell, London, 1749 Aug 4, Sep 12 (Box 2)
  - Levett, Peter. ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Madrid, 1671 Apr 29 (Box 2)
  - "A List of all the Drafts and Papers, belonging to Captn Phillips late one of His Matys Engineers lent mee", 1695 May 30 (Box 2)
  - Lynch, Mr. 2 AL to Sir Robert Southwell, Brussels, 1674 Apr 4, May 22 (Box 2)
  - Madoxe, Philip. ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Whitehall, 1683 Feb 17 (Box 2)
  - Martyn, Thomas. 2 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Antwerp, 1672 Jun 18/8, 21/11 (Box 2)
  - Maynard, Thomas. 7 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Lisbon, 1669 Jun 7/17-1670 Feb 4 (Box 2)
  - "Memoirs of the Family Cromwell ... [and] of the Family Southwell", [ca. 1720] (Box 2)
  - "A Narrative of the Case of John Collins Accomptant in relation to Employments about his Mats Affaires", 1679 (Box 2)
  - Parry, Francis. ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Madrid, 1666 Oct 8 (Box 2)
  - Pirez, Alvaro. [Petition to the East India Company], [n.p.], 1677 Oct 17 (Box 2)
  - Portmore, David Colyear, 1st Earl of, d. 1730. ALS to Edward Southwell, London, 1705 Feb 8 (Box 2)
  - Povey, John. ALS to Edward Southwell, St. James's, 1704 Jan 29 (Box 2)
  - Prescott, Henry. Letter (copy) to Edward Prescott, [n.p.], 1689 Sep 17 (Box 2)
  - Ranelagh, Richard Jones, 1st Earl of, 1636?-1712. [Account of debts due since 1679 Aug 11 totalling £57,806], [n.p.], 1679 Nov 25 (Box 2)
  - Recher, Mr. AL to Edward Southwell, [n.p.], 1704 Jan 18 (Box 2)
  - "A Relation of ye state of Affairs in several Parts of ye East Indies in 1672", [ca. 1672] (Box 2)
  - Rich, Charles. LS to Edward Southwell, Highlake, 1705 Apr 5 (Box 2)
  - St. George, George Gerbier
    - ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Tangier, 1669 Jun 23 (Box 3)
    - ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Tangier, 1673 Oct 15/25 (Box 3)
  - Salinas, Bernardo de. 4 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Brussels and Maestricht, 1672 Jan 20-Apr 7 (Box 3)
  - Sampson, John
    - ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, London, 1690 Jul 3 (Box 3)
    - [Petition to Lord Arlington], [n.p.], n.d. (Box 3)
  - Sancroft, William, Abp. of Canterbury, 1617-1693. [Declaration regarding the Seven Bishops], [n.p.], 1688 May 18 (Box 3)
  - Searchfield, William. 2 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Tercena Islands, 1669 Jun 29, Jul 13 (Box 3)
  - Shelburne, Henry Petty, 1st Earl of, 1675-1751. ALS to Edward Southwell, Dublin, 1704 Aug 24 (Box 3)
  - Shelton, Maurice. ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Barningham, 1679 Nov 19 (Box 3)
  - Shelton Family. [Notes on the Genealogy of the Shelton Family], [ca. 1700] (Box 3)
  - South Sea Company. "Abstract of the Present State of South Sea Strode", 1720 Oct (Box 3)
  - Southwell, Edward
    - "Account of Fiants sealed from Christmas 1751 ... to Christmas [1752]", 1751-52 (Box 3)
    - "A prospect of the Rent Roll of the New Market house of 1711", [ca. 1711] (Box 3)
  - Southwell, Sir Robert, 1635-1702
    - AL (draft) to John Ellis, [n.p.], 1664 Oct 13 (Box 3)
    - Letter (copy) to John Ellis, [n.p.], 1697 Oct 14 (Box 3)
    - 5 AL (drafts) to Jack Elwes, London, 1662 Feb 14-1664 Jun 20 (Box 3)
    - 4 AL (drafts) to Lord Ormonde, Kings Weston, 1684 May 10-1687 Mar 17 (Box 3)
    - [Copy of the Lord Chamberlain's remarks on Lord Bath's Book of Orders], London, 1683 May (Box 3)
    - "A deed ... between Robert Southwell Esq. & Theodorus Vesey Clerke ye 9th of December 1676", 1676 Dec 9 (Box 3)
    - "Discourse with E. of R.", [n.p.], 1668 Jun (Box 3)
      Holograph.
    - "Extracts from the Dean of Lincoln's Sermon at Whitehall", [n.p.], n.d. (Box 3)
    - [Memoranda and papers], [1660 and later] (Box 3)
    - [Memoranda of Lord Ormonde's letters], Dublin, 1684 Jan 6-Nov 12 (Box 3)
    - [Memoranda on religious subjects], [1680 or later] (Box 3)
      Holographs.
    - Memorandum for Lord Claredon, [n.p.], Mar 16 (Box 3)
    - Memorial to Lord Albemarle on the French Ambassador to The Hague, The Hague, 1685 (Box 3)
    - [Notes from Grotius], n.d. (Box 3)
    - [Notes on Dutch ships], [ca. 1670] (Box 3)
    - [Queries concerning styles of address to be used by the king to various other persons], n.d. (Box 3)
  - "A State of the Trade to Sweden as it Stood before the Prohibition", [ca. 1700] (Box 3)
  - Strafford, Thomas Wentworth, 3d Earl of, 1672-1739. ALS to Edward Southwell, Berlin, 1704 Jan 10 (Box 3)
  - Trelawny, [Charles?, 1654-1731]. 3 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Rees & Utrecht, 1673 May 16-Oct 6 (Box 3)
  - Warre, Richard. 2 ALS to Sir Robert Southwell, Whitehall, 1690 Jun 12, 18 (Box 3)
  - William III, King of Gt. Brit., 1650-1702
    - Letter (copy) to Philip William, Elector Palatine, Whitehall, 1690 Jan 23 (Box 3)
    - Letter (copy) to the Duke of Savoy, Camp de Niery, 1690 Jun 26 (Box 3)
  - [William, Duke of Gloucester, d. 1700] "Memorial touching the Funeral of His Highness the Duke of Gloucester", 1700 Jul 30 (Box 3)
  - Wogan, Nicholas. "The Case of Nicholas Wogan", [n.p.], [ca. 1720] (Box 3)
  - Six folders of unsorted Southwell material., 6 (Box 3)